Zubair Mushtaq Data Engineer BI Developer

linkedin.com/in/zubair-mushtaq

Summary

Microsoft Certified Azure Data Engineer and Power BI Data Analyst. Have 3+ years of experience Working in Multiple Domains and Company Types. Have Strong Understanding of Data Modelling, Warehouse Design, DAX Language Principles, Team and client handling. Have Experience in Talend, Databricks, Data Factory, Data Lake and Synapse. Experience in other BI Tools Such as Tableau, Qlik Sense, Cognos.

Work History

Data Engineer, tenx.ai, Islamabad	09/2022-Present
Data Engineer, xadtechnologies.com (Telco-company), Islamabad	09/2021-08/2022
Business Intelligence Developer, Strategic Testing Service Pvt Ltd, Islamabad	02/2021-09/2021

Projects

Financial Domain

- Implement incremental load, surrogates' key generation, type casting, Upsert, populating dimensions and facts in Azure Data Factory and Talend.
- lead the POC transforms the data with PySpark through Databricks and data lake, create views in synapse and visualize in Power BI.
- Developed Power BI Reports Using Measures, Calculated columns, Time Intelligence tables, Custom theming, Calculations like YoY%, QoQ%, MoM% Growth, YTD, QTD, MTD, WTD etc in 3 days.

Telecom Domain

- I consolidated North and South datasets into a single Google Sheets implementing a warehouse in 1 day, enabling centralized reporting for the PMO, which previously lacked a unified data repository for comprehensive analysis.
- Developed Power BI Dashboards, Tableau Dashboard Using Marks, Calculated fields, Parameters, dual axis, advanced LOD Calculations like YoY%, QoQ%, MoM% Growth, YTD, QTD, MTD, WTD etc in 1 week.

Banking Domain

- Reduced the ETL time from 12 hours to 3.5 hours.
- Participate in Data Warehouse Implementation on Khushali Microfinance Bank in Vertica.
- Developed Reports and Dashboards in IBM Cognos in a single day.

Transportation Domain

- Spearheaded a Data modelling strategy for a warehouse for Govia Thameslink Railway UK in MySQL, Union 24 tables with same columns into one in order to fulfil client Dashboarding requirements.
- Load the data from csv into MySQL tables in Talend Open Studio.
- Developed 3 Dashboards in 1 week in Power BI Using Bridge Tables, Power Query, Creating Time Intelligence tables, Calculated Columns, Measures, Color Theory, Bookmarks etc.

Skills and Technologies

- Programming Languages: SQL, PySaprk, DAX,LOD,M-Language.
- On-Premises Tools: MS Power BI, Tableau, Olik Sense, IBM Cognos, RDBMS, Talend.
- Cloud Services: ADLS Gen2, Databricks, ADF, Azure Synapse Analytics, Azure Auto ML and Azure ML Designer.

Certifications

- PL-300: Microsoft Certified: Power BI Data Analyst Associate.
- DP-203: Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Engineer Associate.

Education

BS Computer Science, Bahria University, Islamabad

09/2016-02/2021

Soft Skills

- Mentored employees of 3 departments about the mechanics of Power BI.
- Spearheaded the training workshops on Power BI and Tableau.

Portfolio

shorturl.at/chF19